All
right, guys. I don't know exactly when
this emerged, the Body Masters low back
machine. It could have been like the
'9s. I stumbled across it in the early
2000s, and it was right around the time
that I invented the hip thrust, which
was 2006. Now, I looked at this machine
and I'm like, "Look at this picture.
That looks like a hip thrust. That
doesn't look like it's back extension.
That looks like it's hip extension. If
you spin this picture around, that looks
like it's a hip thrust." So, I get on
here. I did a set and I'm like, "Oh my
god, my glutes are on fire." So, I
actually wrote about it in my first
glute ebook. I said, "This is probably
the best glute exercise in existence.
The only problem is there's some flaws
with the machine. the weight stack only
goes up to 250 lbs and you can quickly,
you know, perform it for 30 plus reps
and you need to keep adding weight. What
are you going to get to a point where
you're doing 50 60? Now, in the early
2000s, it was also thought that
lightweight was inferior to heavy weight
for muscle hypertrophy. And that has
since been debunked. Now, we know that
you can grow just as much muscle from
lightweight compared to heavy weight.
But back then, we didn't know that yet.
And so, I thought, well, too bad you
can't add weight to the stack. If you
could, this would be amazing. But also,
this was too narrow, this foot peg.
Like, why did this foot peg go out
further? And my knees would spread wider
than this pad. But even back then, I
recognized that this has the potential
to be the greatest glute exercise in
existence. So, in the meantime, I was
always on a quest to replicate this. You
could see along the way, like in 2013,
here's me doing a banded back attack we
called it, but your knees are bent and
you're basically doing the same motion
with bands. But this is dangerous. What
happens if those bands came off or snap
back at you? So, this didn't stick, but
I did love the way it felt. You can do
it off a glute ham developer, but yeah,
looks really dangerous. I've also
experimented with it with my clients
over the years. We've done all sorts of
variations, and they always love it.
They think it's amazing. Now, two years
ago, I finally found a used unit. I got
it shipped to Fort Lauderdale and I used
it here in my gym and my clients loved
it. And I loved it. You know why? I
started adding weight onto this lever.
So, you push back, you raise the weight
stack, but then I'd add 25 lb plates to
here. I'd add like three or four 45 lb
plates. And this is a long lever. So,
that adds a lot of resistance. I would
also do enhanced eccentrics where my
clients would go back, but I would push
down and overload the eccentrics. So,
this bar lends itself well to eccentric
overload, which makes it amazing. It's
one of the most friendly ways to be able
to kind of like assist the concentric
and resist the eccentric, but it still
had the original flaws where my knees
spread out and my feet struggled to stay
on the platform. So, my friend Arturo
saw this unit and he decided to remake
it, but he made it even better. I
present to you guys the glute builder
kneeling glute isolator. I think he
should have called it the kneeling hip
thrust because it's a hip thrust. Now
glute builder teamed up with Precore.
They sell it. Have a chance to get this
machine. It is my favorite glute
machine. As you can see the longer foot
plate, the wider mat for kneeling and
even more variables to adjust. You have
the same foot adjustment. So this is
your tibia length. You have the same hip
adjustment which is your femur length.
You can adjust the back pad to be in
different positions and this corresponds
to your spine length. We used to put
this higher up on the back, but now
we're putting it lower on the back
because it leads to less incidence of
low back pain. Same with looking down.
So if you look down, you'll be less
prone to hyperextend your back and you
can adjust the range of motion as well.
So this is your hip flexion mobility. So
you can go deeper or more shallow. But
when we started using a glute loop
around the knees, that's when it became
a game changer. I told our tour, I said,
"Hey, my knees keep spreading and that
throws me off cuz my knees as the set
goes on spread outwards and I need them
to stay in place." So, I thought about
having like like bumper lanes to prevent
that. And he said, "Just wear a glute
loop." And I'm like, "Why didn't I think
of that?" Because to me, this was always
for providing resistance where you'd
want to abduct. No, wearing this just
prevents your knees from spreading. So
you put your feet low on this platform.
You don't have your toes here. You get
low down and make sure your heels are
against it. Wear the glute loop. Make
sure this is the perfect length. Make
sure that the settings are all perfect.
And then like I said, look down, thrust
your hips into the pad, hump the pad,
and make sure you use a full range of
motion. So that means tap down on every
rep and get a full squeeze, reach full
hip hyperextension on every repetition.
But what really makes the kneeling glute
isolator superior is the way that you
can load resistance. So here's the plate
peg. This can load eight 45 lb plates.
If you have thinner plates, it could
load even more. But I am freakishly
strong at this. And it still can
accommodate me, someone who's been
training glutes for decades and doing
hip thrust for decades. And I'm still
fine here with the eight plates. I can
only do that for 10 reps. You can also
do combined plates and bands to make it
an even resistance curve. So, if you do
all plates, it's harder in the start but
easier at the end. This would make the
resistance challenge more in the
lengthen position and less in the
shortened muscle position. If you put
plates and bands on, then it's an even
resistance curve, challenging the muscle
throughout the entire range of motion.
If you use all band resistance, it's
easier in the lengthen position and then
harder in the shortened position. So
less in the stretch, more in the
squeeze. So if you study hypertrophy
science, this is a very hot topic right
now. Many muscles benefit with regards
to hypertrophy when they're trained in
the lengthen position, but not all of
them. And with the glutius maximus, it's
currently up for debate. We've got two
studies supporting a lengthen position
and three studies showing that they seem
to be equal. Now, the studies supporting
the length of position involve Kubo
2019, and it showed that deeper squats
grew significantly more glutes and
adductors than shallow squats. And that
makes sense. The deeper you go, the more
you're going to use your hips. Now,
there are some flaws with that study
because the shallow squats could have
just done a knee bend. They just looked
at knee angle. They didn't look at hip
angle. Nevertheless, that's one in favor
of training the glutes at longer length.
And then the second paper hasn't been
published yet. This was conducted by
Mao. It was presented as a conference
abstract and it showed that
straight-legged kickbacks on the
multi-hip machine done in the lengthen
position just lengthen partials were
superior for growing the glutes compared
to full range hip extensions. So that's
another in support of training the
glutes at long lengths. The other three
papers are Plotkin 2023. This one showed
that squats tied hip thrust for glutius
maximus growth. And if you think about
squats stretch your glutes more and
they're harder in the stretch, whereas
hip thrusts involve less hip range of
motion and they're harder in the squeeze
position. So if long lengths and high
torque at long lengths were all that,
the squat would have greatly
outperformed the hip thrust. But they
tied. And the reason why this is
important is because if you're okay with
doing more volume, you can handle much
more volume with hip thrust than you can
squats. Squats beat up your body a lot
more than hip thrust. All right, the
next study is Cassiono 2024. And this
showed that stiff leg deadlifts and leg
press did not grow the glutes as much as
stiff leg deadlifts, leg press, and hip
thrust. Okay, you could say, "No
kidding. That's obvious. This group did
more volume. They did three exercises.
This group did two exercises, but the
glute growth was linear, meaning six
sets of leg press and stiff leg
deadlifts grew the glutes 6.1%.
And stiff legs, leg press, and hip
thrust grew the glutes 9.3%. So, triple
the glute growth. When you continue to
add sets, it's not linear. You should
see it tapering off. So, the fact that
it's linear means that the hip thrust
could be really good for glutes,
potentially better than leg press and
stiff legs. And then finally, we have
the Bartholomew 2024 paper, and it
showed that squats and step-ups tied hip
thrust and reverse hypers for glutius
maximus growth. So again, squats and
step-ups involve more stretch and more
torque at long lengths, whereas hip
thrust and reverse hypers are more of a
squeeze exercise and they challenge
endrange hip extension more and they
tied for glute growth. So it's kind of
up in the air. What an irrational
scientific person would say is do both.
You should do some exercise that work
you in the lengthen position and some
exercise that work you in the shortened
position. And I brought all this up
because with this kneeling glute
isolator, you can challenge the lengthen
portion or the shortened position just
by altering the resistance profile to be
to be all plates, all bands, or a
combination of plates and bands. I'm
going to do one set of each of those.
All plates to challenge the lengthen
position, plates and bands to make it an
even resistance challenge throughout the
full range, and all bands to challenge
the shorten muscle position. I want to
tell you guys, the glutes do not
activate that well in the lengthen
position. For some reason, when you get
down deep in a full stretch, the glutes
kind of shut down. They do not have high
activation. They max out their
activation in the squeeze position. And
so, they may not involve that high of
passive muscle forces in the stretch
compared to other muscles. And they
could grow more from training at the
optimal length for active tension, which
appears to be closer to full hip
extension. But we don't have any studies
on the glutius maximus. looking at the
micro anatomy of the glutius maximus to
analyze the length tension relationship.
So it's just a guess for now. So what we
need are more anatomical studies, more
hypertrophy studies figuring out how
muscle grows and more training studies
looking at topics like what grows the
glutes more all plates versus all bands.
That would be a cool study, especially
if it was autoregulated based on your
recovery. Like it wasn't volume equated.
You could do as many sets as you wanted
as long as you felt recovered. All
right. Some of you might find this very
interesting. The evolution of the
kneeling hip thrust. So, couple images
from my ebook in 2009 using the Body
Master's low back. You'll notice I state
this needs more load or it would be the
best glute exercise if you could just
add more load. And then here I am in in
2008, my Scottsdale Garage Gym doing a
banded variation out of the power rack.
Well, we were doing that, you know, 20
years ago. And then here's a a video
from 2011. This is when I lived in
Auckland, New Zealand. Here's me doing a
a bent leg back attack, I called it,
with the band. But that's pretty
dangerous. What if that band snapped
back? And then fast forward to 2019.
Here I am using a cable column. This was
so great, but the setup's kind of tough.
And then similar concept using a band,
but you need a strong partner. But we
love this. This is my one of my coaches
from San Diego Sterner. Couple years
later, this is my ex-girlfriend Jackie.
Here's us in Tampa. I stumbled across a
gym, Optimum Gym, that had a unit. And
that caused me to finally find my own
and buy it. And here I am in 2023 using
it with my client Diana. You can see I
widened the base. But now we don't need
a wider base. We just put a band around
the knees. That was Arturo's idea. Then
you see Stephy squats in 2023
overloading the eccentric phase, which
is an awesome idea to make it harder um
due to the limited weight stack. Here uh
you see me adding plates to the front. I
never thought of this and this is a a
way around you know adding extra loading
when you get too strong to the stack. So
had I known about these you know 20
years prior I would have loved this
machine even more. But that all became
obsolete in 2024 when glute builder my
friend Arturo remade the unit and he
solved all the problems with the body
masters unit. But still I didn't have a
glute builder at all my locations. So,
in in Fort Lauderdale, I'm using the
glute builder, but in Vegas, I'm
prescribing, you know, these banded
variations still. Here's Elizabeth um in
Vegas using the the glute rack in the
wall. Here's Lely and Mermaid Bri and
Sarah. My clients from San Diego using
um bands out of the power rack. So,
yeah, you'll see this continuous quest
to uh you know, improve upon and and
come up with variations. But now with
the glute builder model, it's perfect.
We don't need any of these variations.
So, let me do one set of each and you
can be the judge.
[Music]
Oh,
Okay. So, now remove the plates and go
12 bands. So, we already have six on
here. These are the heavy bands.
And these are the extra heavy, the
hardest. So, this is 12 bands. So, that
is a ton of tension,
especially as you get to end range hip
extension.
[Music]
So there you have it. There's three
different resistance profiles. Same
range of motion, same positioning, but
drastically different torque angle
curves. If I had to choose which is best
for hypertrophy, I would choose the
third option because I can do six hard
sets of that and the next day I'm not
sore. When you target a muscle at a
shorter length, it doesn't create as
much muscle damage. Conversely, when you
stress a muscle at a longer length, more
damage occurs. And so, it could be the
case that on a set per set basis, the
first option is more productive, the one
that was hardest at the longer muscle
length. But let's say you did four
really hard sets of that, you might be
sore for a few days. You might be
fatigued. Whereas the latter option, you
could do that three times a week and
still recover. You could do three, four,
maybe even up to six sets three times a
week. So, 18 total sets. Again, we're
acting like this is the only exercise
you can perform. In reality, you can do
a variety of exercises. Obviously, you
can do like a squat or lunge type
movement, a thrust bridge type movement,
a hinge, and an abduction movement. And
you can do four exercises, maybe even
five, three times a week, and you can
recover just fine. But I'm just giving
you guys food for thought because this
is a fascinating topic. It's also the
fastest growing topic in sports science
right now with 15 new studies emerging
in the last year alone. The main thing I
want to point out is this is an awesome
piece of equipment, the kneeling glute
isolator. I loved it in the early 2000s
when it was the Body Masters low back
machine. I've loved the different
variations over the years that I tried,
but nothing was as good as the glute
builder kneeling glute isolator. So,
hats off to Arturo. If your gym has
this, definitely learn how to use it.
It's my favorite glute exercise. Like I
said, I like it more than the hip
thrust, but it is a kneeling hip thrust
that takes your quad out of it. Hope you
enjoyed this quick video. If you like
what you saw, please give it a like.
Please leave me a comment, tell me what
you think, and definitely make sure
you're subscribed to my channel. I'm
Breis, aka the glute guy.